A Guide to the Donald D. Van Slyke papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA203
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Biographical material, photographs, bibliography, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical memoir NAS v. 48 (1976) by Baird Hastings. Some copies of annual reports (excerpts)
  - New York Times obituary
  - Sendroy Julius "In appreciation, Donald Dexter Van Slyke, 1883-1971" CLINICAL CHEMISTRY 17 (1971) 670-672
  - John T. Edsall, "Carbon dioxide transport in blood: Equilibrium between red cells and plasma. The work of D.D. Van Slyke and L.J. Henderson, 1920-1928". Hist. Phil. Life Sci., 7 (1985), 105-120
    In folder in "Biographical file".
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Dr. Edsall
- Administrative correspondence, 1907-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - April-May application to RIMR and letters of recommendation, 1907
  - Report of the war activities of Hospital chemistry department; written at suggestion of T.M. Prudden, 1918 June
  - Correspondence regarding use of name to help raise money to use for medical supplies for China, 1937
- Administrative correspondence, 1938-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Cole and Dr. Gasser related to Aug.-Jan. leave of absence to be visiting professor at Peiping Medical College, 1940
  - Some personal notes. Thank you for flowers sent by Institute at death of Rena Mosher Van Slyke Some handwritten acceptances of invitations [apparatus and equipment], 1948
  - List of materials/sold to Brookhaven National Laboratory from RIMR at request of Dr. Van Slyke on retirement from Institute
- Oral History from a five hour audio taped interview with Dr. Van Slyke on May 27 and 28, 1969 by Peter D. Olch of History of Medicine Division, National Library of Medicine, 1969 May 27-28; 1 volume, 144 pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Indexed.
  Includes biography; bibliography; copy of personal history as prepared for Dr. Gasser.
- Roos, Albert and Boron, Walter F. The buffer value of weak acids and bases: origin of the concept, and the first mathematical derivation and application to physico-chemical systems the work of M. Koppel and K. Spiro, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Translation of article with significance for Van Slyke work.
- Photographic album presented to D.D. Van Slyke by The Medical Department of Brookhaven National Laboratory in honor of Dr. Van Slyke's 80th birthday, 1963 March (Box 2)
- "Donald Dexter Van Slyke. The Twentieth Century Iatrochemist" (Box 2)
- Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Edgar Stillman/D.D. Van Slyke. [re] Van Slyke illness and encouragement. Handwritten, 1918 November 11
  - A. Baird Hastings/D.D. Van Slyke. Primarily [re] Hastings scientific work, 1935 January 22
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. /D.D. Van Slyke. [re] declining dinner invitation for medical aid to China stating reasons, 1935 November 2
  - D.D. Van Slyke/Kate [Stillman?]. Condolences on husband, Edgar [Stillman's] death. Handwritten, 1967 August 26
- Clippings (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Custodial History
  Copies orginated from the Else Van Slyke collection.
  Copies Includes:
  - J.A. LeClerc. "Obituary of Lucius Lincoln Van Slyke". Journal of the Association of Official Agricultural Chemists, May 1932, iii-iv, 1932 May
  - "To Donald D. Van Slyke - First Scientific Achievement Award," Chemical and Engineering News, Vol 40, no 27, p 60
  - "Dr. Donald D. Van Slyke. Contemporaries", pp 61-62. Irvine H. Page editorial. Modern Medicine, pp 67-68
- Obituaries (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Includes.
  - Aura Edward Severinghaus. "Donald D. Van Slyke Third President of ABMAC. The ABMAC Bulletin Vol 32, nos 3, 4, Mar-Apr 1971, pp 1-3, 1971 March-April
  - "Biochemist Van Slyke Dies: Kin Lives Here. " Evening Journal, Wilmington, Delaware, p 42, 1971 May 6
  - Medical World News, p 46, 1971 May 28
- Photocopies of articles, clippings etc (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Originated from the collection of Else Van Slyke.
  - "Rockefeller Institute Donald Dexter Van Slyke to receive Willard Gibbs Medal". The Chemical Bulletin, Vol 26, no 3, p 69, 1939 March
  - "Chemist Diagnoses the Possible - Dr. Donald D. Van Slyke". (On receipt of AMA's first scientific achievement award). Medical Tribune, 1962 June 25
  - Symposium on chemistry in medicine. Sponsored by Medical Department, Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1963 Mar 28-29, in honor of Dr. Van Slyke's 80th birthday. Program, 1963 March 28-29
  - "Johnson names 11 for Science Medals" (Includes D.D. Van Slyke). New York Times, Sunday, Dec 12, 1965, p 78, 1965 December 12
  - Presentation of the National Medal of Science, The White House, 1966 February 10
    Includes program, list of medalists, list of President's committee on the National Medal of Science, and Lyndon B. Johnson remarks.
  - Geneva, 7th International Congress of Swiss Society of Clinical Chemistry, [re] D.D. Van Slyke address. Medicine et Hygiene (special issue), 1969 September 8-13
  - Obituaries, 1972
    Includes: A. Baird Hastings. "Donald Dexter Van Slyke 1883-1971." Journal of Biological Chemistry 247 (1972) 1635-1640.
  - Symposium at University of Ulm honoring D.D. Van Slyke. Program (in German), 1972 February 19
- Portraits of D.D. Van Slyke, 2 folders
  - High school graduate, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Pekin, China, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Portraits by Louis Schmidt, RIMR, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Portrait by Blauvelt-Haulenbeck, RIMR, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Portrait. Multiple copies, 1 signed by D.D. Van Slyke, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Photographs. Group photographs of Brookhaven National Laboratory staff, 1955-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Includes: 1955 and 1956 with identification, 1958, 1963, 1965, 1969, nd. Photographs of A. Baird Hastings, John Plazin.
- Portraits of colleagues (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Eggert Mtiller 1928, Peter? (in 1955, 1956 Brookhaven group photos identified as W.L. Hughes)., Christen Lundsgaard (d. 1930), M. Gomberg, Lee Farr ca 1936, John P. Peters 1955?, Frank (UNREADABLE). 1960, Glenn E. Cullen 1932, A. Baird Hastings 1949, P.A. Levene, 1928 1930 1932 1936 1949 1955 1956 1960
- Photographs, miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lewis Dahl, D.D. Van Slyke and George Cotzias, In color, nd
  - D.D. Van Slyke and son, Keller, skiing, nd
  - Photo album. The International Institute of Scientific Cooperation, Schloss Reisensburg (Donan) of interiors and exteriors, presented to D.D. Van Slyke
  - Mounted black and white photograph of group at a concert. Unidentified, undated
  - Photograph in color of David Barr, Phil Bard, D.D. Van Slyke, Randall Edwards, Magnus Gregersen, of China International Foundation grant committee, 1964 July
  - Mounted photograph of probably first Mrs. Lucius Van Slyke
  - Mural, possibly at Research Institute at Dlea Deau, Montreal, 1985 November 7
    Includes thank you note from the Genests. Jacques Genest was head of Institute (per R.M. Archibald.) Prints in color of mural. [7 Nov 1985 R.M. Archibald/RU Archives - Description of Ceramic Mural in Lobby, 3 pp. at Institut de Diagnostic et de Recherches Cliniques de Montreal, Clinical Research Institute of Montreal.].
- Memorabilia
  - Bronx medal commemorating 70th birthday of Bernarr MacFadden long distant women's swimming, 1938 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Chemical Bulletin, Vol 26, no 5, May 1939. Booklet. [re] Willard Gibbs medal to Van Slyke, 1939 May (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes program listing D.D. Van Slyke "The Development of Controlled Oxygen Therapy"; and Franklin C. McLean "Donald Dexter Van Slyke" pp 137-139.
  - The Lambda News, May 1950, p 5. "News of Donald D. Van Slyke," alumni of Beta Theta pi fraternity, University of Michigan, 1950 May (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Eugene W. Beesley, President, Eli Lilly/D.D. Van Slyke. [re] Van Slyke's 5 years service on Lilly research grants committee, 1956 August 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Certificate for 50 years membership at First Presbyterian Church, Geneva, New York, 1956 October 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - [re] Radio of Free Asia, 1964 Certificate (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Boston, Mass., 14th annual convention of American College of Cardiology. D.D. Van Slyke receives honorary fellowship award. Convocation booklet, 1965 February 20 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New York State Dept of Health certificate of qualification in clinical chemistry, 1965 July 28 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - photograph of RIMR Campus, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "D.D. Van Slyke Mar 1, 1896" scotch taped on cardboard with handwritten note, 1896 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook [re], undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - John P. Peters and Donald D. Van Slyke. "Quantitative Clinical Chemistry: Interpretation". Vol I (1931); Vol II (1932), 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes reviews and letters of congratulations on publications; advertising leaflets.
  - D.D. Van Slyke and others. "Observation on the Courses of Different Types of Bright's Disease and a Resultant Change in Renal Anatomy. Vol 17, Williams and Wilkins, Baltimore, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes reviews, list of names requesting monograph and letters of congratulations. Reprinted in Medicine 9 (1930) 257-286.
- Furniture appraisal 1960. Catalogue and appraisal of property belonging to Donald D. Van Slyke, compiled by Consolidated Appraisal, New York (Box 3, Folder 11)
- New York Times, [re] D.D. Van Slyke receiving Philip A. Conne gold medal of The Chemists Club of New York. Newspaper clipping, 1937 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- [re] American Chemical Society, Willard Gibbs Award at Chicago, ACS meeting, 1939 May (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Includes program, The Chemical Bulletin, May 1939 and newspaper clippings from the New York Times, Pittsburgh Press and The Bronxville Press.
- D.D. Van Slyke receives honorary M.D. from University of Amsterdam, 1962 May 28 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Includes calendar of trip kept by Van Slyke (handwritten), photograph of D.D. Van Slyke and others at degree granting ceremony, correspondence, typescript of Prof Borst's address, newspaper clippings, University of Amsterdam bulletin and letter of congratulations from J.P. Wibault.
- D.D. Van Slyke delivers principal address. "On the Dedication of the Reactor of the Institute of Nuclear Science of Tsing Hua University" Taipei, 1961 December 5 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Includes: correspondence, typescript of Van Slyke's presentation, booklet "Research in Free China. Taiwan's Academia Sinia 1927-1961." photographs and miscellaneous items.
- American Medical Assoc (AMA) first scientific achievement award to D.D. Van Slye, Chicago, 111th annual meeting of the AMA, 1962 June (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Includes correspondence, photograph of D.D. Van Slyke and Hugh H. Hussey, miscellaneous items, clippings announcing award in various publications, and letters of congratulations.
- Symposiums in honor of Van Slyke's 80th birthday (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Includes correspondence, programs, and guest lists of.
  - Medical Dept, Brookhaven National Laboratory. Symposium on chemistry in medicine, 1963 March 28-29
  - New York City, American Microchemical Society, 1963 April 19
- Hospital Patient Records "Nephrotics" age 15 and over. Original copy. Rockefeller Hospital, 1924-1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Research records "Nephrotics" Rockefeller Hospital, 2 folders
  - A-K (Graphic charts) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - L-Z (Graphic charts) (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Copy negatives/prints, 8x10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Peking Union Medical College. Group photograph, 1921
  - Peking Union Medical College. Group photograph. (different pose), 1921
  - Bronxville, NY, 1922-1924
  - [Copenhagen?] Elsa, Kell, Rena Van Slyke, 1932
  - Don playing tennis at RI (cover/color original) of the Physicians' Bulletin May-June 1948, by Golinkin]
  - D.D. Van Slyke and Lieut. Gen. Robert Kho-Sheng Lim, printed in News of China. United China Relief, vol 3, no. 6, p. 1, 1944
  - New York Times. 25 May 1962. "L.I. Research Chemist to Get A.M.A. Award". Newspaper clipping
  - telegram from Robert Lim/Donald Van Slyke, 28 Mar 1947
  - R.I. Van Slyke in middle of front row, P.A.T. Levene (with mustache) to his left, 1912
- Extra photographic prints (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Photocopies of photographs owned by Karl Keller Van Slyke of D.D. Van Slyke. (1960s?) (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Articles copied from collection of K. Keller Van Slyke in 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Chemical Bulletin, 1939 May
  - Grit, 1960 October 6
  - News of China 3 (1944) 1
  - Chemical and Engineering News, Front Cover, 1094, 1953 March 16
  - ABMAC Bulletin 17 (1956) 1, 5-6
- Donald D. Van Slyke biographic material from Elsa Van Slyke (Box 5, Folder 5)
- 5x7 copy negatives or smaller prints (Box 6)
  Scope and Contents
  [RMA #'s = nos. assigned by Dr. D.D. Van Slyke portrait by Randall. RMA#1 Reginald M. Archibald]
  - L.L. Van Slyke home in Geneva, NY ca. 1907 RMA#1a
  - Lucius Lincoln Van Slyke (father) RMA#2
  - Geneva, NY home where D.D. Van Slyke grew up. Interior room of house RMA#3
  - Uncle Morell Quackenbush and L.L. Van Slyke 1980 RMA#4
  - Lawrence P. Van Slyke, half brother of D.D. Van Slyke, Fall 1905 or Spring 1906 RMA#4a, 1905-1906
  - Lucius, Elsa, and Donald Van Slyke RMA#5a
  - Elsa, Rena, Donald, and Kell Van Slyke, Mountain Lakes, NJ 1921 RMA#6
  - Donald and Rena Van Slyke on their way to China 1921 RMA#7
  - Hedwig Van Slyke (L.L. Van Slyke's third wife) RMA#11
  - Lucius and Hedwig Van Slyke family photograph when married 2 June 1926 in Honolulu RMA#12, 1926 June 2
  - D.D. Van Slyke Northwestern University receives honorary degree RMA#13a, 1940 June 15
  - D.D. Van Slyke receiving honorary degree at Northwestern RMA#13b, 1940 June 15
  - D.D. Van Slyke, Koenigssee, Germany RMA#15, 1930 August
  - Rena, Elsa, Donald, Kell Christmas Muerren RMA#16, 1929
  - Kell, Rena, Elsa, Donald on board the De Grasse RMA#17, 1930 September 3
  - Elsa Van Slyke in Bronxville, New York. RMA#19, 1943
  - Rena and D.D. Van Slyke RMA#20, 1943
  - Kell Van Slyke RMA#21
  - Christmas with the A. Baird Hastings at Central Park West, NY City [Identifications on envelope] RMA#22, 1945
  - Christmas with the Hastings at Central Park West, NY City of Baird Hastings and Donald D. Van Slyke. RMA#23, 1945
  - Donald and Kell Van Slyke skiing,. RMA#24, 1947
  - Donald D. Van Slyke portrait bordered by apparatus. Cover of The Chemical Bulletin, Vol 26, no 5, May 1939. RMA#26, 1939 May
  - Newspaper clipping photograph of D.D. Van Slye with Helen Keller and Miss Polly Thompson at formal dinner in Miss Keller's honor at the New York World's Fair, RMA#27, 1940 October 6
  - Donald D. Van Slyke in the laboratory used in The Chemical Bulletin, with article by Franklin C. McLean, "Donald Dexter Van Slyke." RMA#28, 1939 May
  - Donald D. Van Slyke on steps of home in Geneva, New York. RMA#31
  - Cornell Experimental Station. Lucius L. Van Slyke worked here. Dairy and Biological Building. RMA#32
  - Dairy building. RMA#33
  - Cornell Experimental Station, Geneva, NY Chemical laboratory. RMA#34
  - Donald D. Van Slyke and his assistant. RMA#35
  - D.D. Van Slyke receiving honorary degree at Yale, New Haven, Conn, ca 1925. D.D., Van Slyke's first honorary? RMA#36
  - Left to right: L.L. Van Slyke, father of D.D.V.S., Rena Mosher (spelling?), D.D.V.S.'s daughter, D.D. Van Slyke, Julia Van Slyke, second wife of L.L.V.S. In front: Lawrence P. Van Slyke, son of L.L.V.S. and Julia, ca 1914? RMA#37
  - D.D. Van Slyke ca 1927 with son, Karl Keller Van Slyke. RMA#38
  - D.D. Van Slyke, Photo by J.E. Hale, Geneva, New York. RMA#39
  - D.D. Van Slyke. Photo by CA. Scherer RMA#42
  - D.D. Van Slyke. Photo by Randall RMA#50
  - D.D. Van Slyke, Photo by Hartung. Photo Shop, Peking. RMA#51
  - D.D. Van Slyke and others on way to Ming Tombs, RUA#52, 1922
  - D.D. Van Slyke photograph printed in ABMAC Bulletin 17, no 5, No, 1956 September
- Else Van Slyke collection, 4 oversize packages (Box 6)
  Originated from the Else Van Slyke collection.
  - Photographs and memorabilia, 1; oversize package 1 (Package 1)
    - L.L. Van Slyke portrait with inscription, 1909
    - D.D. Van Slyke portrait taken at Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1962?
    - Mounted print with photograph of Emil Fischer bust and drawings of buildings and apparatus. Dedication "Seinen lieben Schülern und Kollegen zür Erinnerung an gemeinsame Arbeit in Dankborkeit gewidmet von Emil Fischer". Berlin. d.J. OKT. 1912. Entwurf v. Gustav Fischer Gr.-Lichterfelde - Photographie v. Franz Linkhorst-Grunewald nach der Bronce v. Prof. Fritz Klimsch - Charlottenburg
    - Mural. Possibly at Research Institute Dlea Deau in Montreal. (As per R.M. Archibald), 3 copies
      Includes faces of Sir Thomas Lewis, Claude Bernard, J.S.L. Browne, Donald D. Van Slyke.
  - telegram from China. Robert Lim/D.D. Van Slyke on retirement from Presidency of ABMAC and gratitude for help to China. Framed, 2; oversize package 2 (Package 2)
  - 2 brass plates of Beta Theta Pi Fraternity plate and University of Michigan plate, 3; oversize package 3 (Package 3)
  - untitled, 4; oversize package 4 (Package 4)
    - Honorary Doctor of Science Degrees
      - Yale University, diploma, 1925
      - University of Michigan, diploma, 1935
      - Northwestern University, diploma, 1940
      - University of Chicago, diploma, 1941
      - University of London, diploma, 1951
    - Honorary Doctor of Medicine Degrees
      - University of Oslo, diploma, 1938
      - University of Amsterdam, diploma with signature, 1962
    - Medals and Awards
      - Fisher Award in Analytical Chemistry, American Chemical Society, diploma, 1953
      - First Van Slyke Award in Clinical Chemistry, American Association of Clinical Chemists, diploma, 1957
      - National Medal of Science, USA, diploma, 1965
      - Elliott Cresson Award, Franklin Society of Philadelphia, diploma, 1965
      - Distinguished Clinical Chemist Award of The International Federation of Clinical Chemistry, diploma, 1969
    - American Memberships
      - National Academy of Sciences, diploma, 1921
    - Foreign Memberships (Honorary)
      - Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher, diploma, 1932
      - Società Lombarda di Medicina, diploma, 1935
      - Physiological Society letter, 1942
      - Royal Society of Sciences of Upsala, diploma, 1942
      - Danish Society for Internal Medicine, diploma, 1952
      - Société de Pathologie Rénale, letter from Dr. A.A. Osman, 1952
      - Academia Nazionale dei Lincei, Italy, diploma, 1961
      - Danish Academy, diploma, 1956
      - Oesterreichische Gesellschaft für Mikrochemie diploma, 1961
    - Miscellaneous
      - Honorary Member, Staff of NAMRU-2, 3 Jan, Dept of Navy, certificate, 1962
      - Certificate of Appreciation, The War Department, 1946 October 28
- Framed watercolor, Unknown, may be Chinese.
- Van Slyke, D.D. reprints, 4 boxes
  - 1907-1923, 5" letter size (Box 7)
  - 1924-1933, 5" letter size (Box 8)
  - 1934-1944, 1946-1947, 5" letter size (Box 9)
  - 1948-1951, 1960, 2½" letter size (Box 10)